Guide to the Society of the Sigma Xi Chapter, Yale University, Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Society of the Sigma Xi chapter, Yale University, records
1895-1983
RU 744
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3.75
The records consist of correspondence, president's files, by-laws, constitution, minutes, and printed material documenting the operations of the Yale Chapter of the Sigma Xi.
Society of the Sigma Xi. Yale Chapter
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 40 (YRG 40), Records of Yale clubs, societies and organizations.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
The records are arranged by accession.
Biographical / Historical
The Yale Chapter of Sigma Xi was established in 1895. This strictly scientific society, now having 130 chapters across the nation, was founded by Henry Shaler Williams, a graduate from the Class of 1868, Sheffield Scientific School, while he was a professor at Cornell University. When the Yale Chapter was established, active membership was limited to students of the Scientific School but later was opened to other departments of the university. Today the society elects top scholars in science and engineering and also faculty members who have done outstanding work in their fields.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of correspondence, president's files, by-laws, constitution, minutes, and printed material documenting the operations of the Yale Chapter of the Sigma Xi.
College students -- Societies, etc.; Science -- Societies, etc.; Society of the Sigma Xi. Yale Chapter; Yale University -- Societies, etc.; Yale University -- Students
- Records, 1909-1940; Accession 19ND-A-483
  - president's book: correspondence
    - 1922-23 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1923-24 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1924-25 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1925-26 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1926-27 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1927-28 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1928-29 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1929-30 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1930-31 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1931-32 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1932-33 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - 1933-1934 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - 1935-1936 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - 1936-1937 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - 1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - 1938-1939 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - 1939-1940 (Box 3, Folder 18-19)
  - Miscellaneous President's material, 1909, 1928 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous material, lists, 1911-1919 (Box 3)
  - Handbooks, proceedings, and petitions, circa 1911-1923 (Box 3)
  - president's file: Joseph W. Roe, 1910-1911 (Box 3)
  - president's file: Joseph Barrell, 1911-1912 (Box 3)
  - Duties of the President, 1912 (Box 3)
  - President's file, 1912-1913 (Box 3)
  - president's file: Arthur L. Dean, 1913-1914 (Box 3)
  - president's file: L. W. Bahney, 1914-1915 (Box 4)
  - Sigma Xi Quarterly, 1915, 1922 (Box 4)
  - Constitution and by-laws and related matter, 1921-1923 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1922-1925 (Box 4)
  - Nomination blanks, 1920, 1923, undated (Box 4)
  - Notices and miscellaneous correspondence, 1922-1933 (Box 4)
  - Election and initiation banquet material, 1926 (Box 4)
  - Membership cards, 1931, 1933 (Box 4)
  - Simon B. Kleiner election to Sigma Xi, 1911 (Box 4)
- Records, 1895-1983; Accession 1987-A-096
  - Constitution, By-Laws, and Membership Register, 1895-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1 - 2)
  - History, Half-Century Record and, 1886-1936 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Minutes of meetings and Membership Register, 1895-1942 (Box 3, Folder 4 - 5)
  - Proceedings: minutes of meetings, banquet progams, meeting notices, 1941-1983 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Song (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Sigma Xi memorabilia, 1940; Accession 2008-A-137
  - Insignia price list, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Initiation and banquet brochure, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Membership card, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Diploma, 1940 (Box 1)